"How Much Exercise Does It Take
to Boost Immunity?"
Exercise can boost
our immune system by so much
that we can reduce
the number of symptom days
by 25 to 50 percent.
Imagine if there was some drug
that could do that,
it would rake in billions,
whereas,
exercise is free and tends
to only have good side effects.
It doesn't even take much
of a workout to get results.
Studies find that
if you let kids run around
for just six minutes,
the levels of immune cells
circulating in their blood
can increase by 50 percent,
as they pour
from the bone marrow
and redeploy
throughout the body.
Even moderate exercise
can also boost IgA production,
protective antibodies that coat
all of our moist membranes.
Compared to
a sedentary control group,
those who performed
aerobic exercises
for thirty minutes
three times a week
for twelve weeks
had a 50 percent increase
in the levels of IgA
in their saliva
and reported significantly fewer
flu-related symptoms.
Salivary IgA levels
are associated
with lower overall
mortality risk over time,
particularly cancer mortality,
perhaps as a proxy for
immune function more generally,
and you can boost those levels
with exercise.
Exercising may also boost
the activity
of natural killer cells,
our immune soldiers
that focus on eliminating
both tumor cells
and virus-infected cells.
Here are five different types
of cancer
growing in a petri dish,
mostly leukemias
and lymphomas.
Draw blood from people
and drip on some
of their natural killer cells
into the dish,
and they start killing off
the cancer cells.
Okay, but that was blood taken
from someone before exercise.
Draw blood after 30 minutes
of cycling
and drop on the same number
of natural killer cells,
and they each kill cancer
about 60 percent better.
This may be one of the reasons
why exercise
seems to help
both prevent cancer
and improve cancer survival.
Might it improve
vaccination responses?
If aerobic exercise
gets your immune cells
to spill out from your bones,
can't you just slouch
on the couch all year
and just jump up
and take a brisk walk
right before getting the jab?
Studies to this effect
performed on young adults
had inconsistent results,
for example,
improving the antibody response
to a flu vaccine
in women but not men,
or to a meningitis vaccine
in men but not women.
Against half doses
or weaker vaccines,
acute exercise interventions
appeared to work better,
suggesting perhaps
a ceiling effect,
whereby their immune responses
were normally so robust
exercise might not
improve them further.
But maybe it would work more
consistently in older adults?
Sadly, 45-minute moderate
intensity aerobic exercise
right before flu
or pneumonia vaccinations
didn't seem to help
in older adults.
Even two months
of 45-minute moderate intensity
daily activity,
six weeks before and two weeks
after vaccination,
appeared insufficient
to make a difference.
Eccentric resistance exercise,
for example,
slowly lowering heavy dumbbells
after bicep curls
or lateral raises
to inflame the muscles right
before the vaccine goes in
also doesn't seem
to be a viable strategy.
What about exercise to reduce
infection risk directly?
In a study entitled
"Moderate exercise
protects mice from death
due to influenzas virus,"
mice exercised
for 20 to 30 minutes
four hours
after flu virus exposure
and then
each of the next three days
had nearly twice
the survival rate
(18 percent dying
compared to 57 percent dead
in the sedentary group).
There's nothing so dramatic
in the human literature,
but based on a study
that followed
more than a thousand adults
through flu season,
those who exercised
even just a few days a week
were sick
about 40 percent fewer days
than sedentary individuals.
Randomized controlled
interventional trials
back this up.
For example, one study found
that while elderly,
sedentary women randomized
to a mild range of motion
and flexibility calisthenics
control group
had a 50 percent chance
of getting
an upper-respiratory illness
during the fall season,
those randomized to begin
a half-hour-a-day
walking program
dropped their risk down
to 20 percent.
For conditioned athletes,
though,
the risk was just 8 percent.
Exercising could potentially
make our immune systems
more than five times better
at fighting infection.
In a year-long study,
sedentary, postmenopausal women
randomized to 45 minutes
of moderate-intensity exercise
five days per week
were experiencing
three times fewer colds
by the end of the study
compared to the control group,
who were instead randomized
to weekly stretching sessions,
even though the exercise group
only ended up exercising
around four times a week.
A similar study
of younger overweight women
found that 15 weeks
of daily walking
cut the number of days sick
from upper respiratory tract
infections symptoms in half,
though this was due
to cutting the duration
of each episode in half
rather than cutting down
on the frequency of illness.
In terms
of more serious infections,
randomizing older men and women
to one-hour exercise classes
twice a week for two years
did not, unfortunately,
cut down on the risk
of coming down with pneumonia.
Although yoga training
can improve lung function
in the elderly,
it has yet to be shown to help
prevent pneumonia either.
There was, however,
a treatment trial
of yoga breathing exercises
for pulmonary tuberculosis
performed in India.
Compared to
a mindfulness meditation,
"breathing awareness"
control group,
those randomized
to a yoga group
cleared their active infections
faster.
Even "laughter yoga"
might help.
The evolution of laughter
is thought to have been
as an antidote to stress,
the release of nervous energy.
Within 60 minutes of people
watching a comedy video
(complete with "Gallagher's
classic Sledge-O-Matic finale"),
levels of the stress hormone
cortisol in their bloodstreams
were cut by more than half.
Since cortisol acts
as an immunosuppressant,
which is why
cortisol-like steroids
like prednisone are used
for inflammatory
autoimmune diseases,
the drop in cortisol
with laughter may explain
why those laughing heartily
at a humorous video
had improvements
in natural killer cell function
compared to those randomized
to a control group
watching tourism videos.
(Replicating these results today
might be difficult
given the choice
of comedic stimulus:
Bill Cosby.)